[Music]
great hello
and
welcome everyone
it is
just adjusting things it is may 4th may
the 4th of 22 be with you
and we're here in
flab live stream number 43.1
blue i don't know how you do it with
always joining during the theme song
welcome to the actin flab
we're a participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at links on this slide
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
check out activeinference.org
if you want to learn more about what's
happening in the lab and get involved
and participate in the live streams or
any other
activities
all right well we're here in
live stream number 43.1
and are continuing the discussion of the
paper predictive coding a theoretical
and experimental review by baron millage
neil seth and christopher buckley
in 43.0
with maria
we went over some of the background and
context and did like a first pass
on various aspects of the paper but by
no means exhausted it because it's a
long and
very intricate paper and also it touches
on a ton of other areas of more general
interest so there's a lot to discuss
and
in the 43.1 today we'll see where things
go
if you're watching live it would be
awesome to have any questions in the
live chat
otherwise we will just start with some
introductions and pick up with whatever
people are finding salient and exciting
so we'll just start by saying hello and
going from there
i'm daniel and i'm a researcher in
california and thanks a lot blue for
joining
i'm blue i'm a researcher in new mexico
and yeah i'm excited to be here today
this paper was um
really intricate and detailed and
provided a lot of background um that i
don't have because you know there are so
many active papers that i want to read
but i don't have time to get to them all
um because i'm i like to read things
very thoroughly and slowly and carefully
and look up the things that i don't know
and the back references
travel down the scientific rabbit hole
so to speak
so yeah this was a good paper that kind
of helped me you know
shirk all those active responsibilities
that i have and
um came out with more like questions
than than
answers
which
is always a good sign of a good paper
awesome well how about going into the
paper
what questions did you have and maybe
we'll get to how our questions evolved
but what were you expecting
to find in the paper and what questions
were motivating you to seek it
so i i always have had a hard time like
what is the difference between
predictive coding
variational base and active right and
and like i was really hoping that the
paper would kind of lay that out for me
and like no
so like i mean i kind of got a good
historical overview of um how they all
are interlocking and overlapping
which i didn't know before um because
you know all these things none of them
are simple
and there are intricate details in all
of them like you know that i don't know
all the details ins and outs but i think
that this gave a very good like
historical overview of how these things
kind of layer into a nice little
sandwich
great
definitely a good
starting place let's also add
bayesian brain
there to the mix
and
start to look at maybe some similarities
too because they're not exactly like
addressing the same
area and they're compatible often more
compatible than not so getting at what
distinguishes them
is very important
and
like one way that that happened and
it came up in the dot zero was so much
of the paper was dealing with
inference on
the relationship between observations
and unobserved latent states so think
like trying to infer the temperature of
the room given the thermometer readings
and that was so much of the paper and
then
action comes into the picture
in
uh section four five
it's like
predictive coding
the authors write can also be extended
to include action allowing for
predictive coding agents to undertake
adaptive actions without any major
change to their fundamental algorithms
but that's 50 equations deep and so it's
very interesting to see like if those 50
equations are kind of like the stem i
know that the equations are not
sequential and building on each other in
in all of these cases but then
action gets tucked into a bigger picture
very seamlessly and i think that speaks
to the the relevance of distinguishing
how they're similar
and different and
why it matters i guess so how should we
even begin to look at that
so even action actually came up earlier
in the paper before 4.5 so action came
up in um
section 2.3 with dynamical predictive
coding
and generalized coordinates and and this
i thought was a really good
um
example like like i was craving
and still i'm craving like a really
simple example like like it's one thing
you know we talk about the equations we
go through all the letters we compare
this and that but it would be really
great to see a super simple example
works through like from start to finish
using all of these
observable states latent states
complexity accuracy like
it would be really great to see that at
some
point um
and uh if you're listening to this live
stream and want to come on and give like
a guest tutorial on like how do we
actually work these equations into some
very simple problem that we can solve in
real life like i would be more than
happy to
facilitate that presentation um yeah
because i can't even like
i can't jump from like all these
equations into like how does that apply
um but even in in 2.3 this was kind of a
good um
a good
a goodish example a a real life example
about like inferring
you know the velocity and the
acceleration and the jerk um just given
the the observed coordinates um so that
was kind of and it talks here about also
free action
which um
i've not heard before
so instead of minimizing the variational
free energy
it says we must instead minimize the
free action which is f bar
um
and i've not seen or heard it referred
to in that way but it's modeling like
time series of observations
um so like you know you know the
coordinates at time one time two time
three of a of a swinging pendulum for
example um
if you know those coordinates then you
can kind of guess you know how fast is
the object moving and you can infer
these other these other variables so i
haven't seen that free action but it did
even come up before four or five
yes
and it speaks to that
expected free energy efe
which is
what do you expect the free energy to be
and then there's the free energy of the
expected future which one of the authors
has worked on which is kind of a
slightly different variant and then
here's another way
to look at the free energy of some
future time steps
and and it speaks to that difference
between the variational free energy
which is like what you're able to
calculate right now with the information
at hand and looking backwards
and so the more perceptual aspects of
inference can be calculated using the
variational free energy approach
but then any time the future is coming
into play
there's uncertainty about the
observations
as well as even uncertainty about what
actions one will take let alone the
consequences of the actions that one
will take in the future so
we do need a different way to calculate
it and then as you're kind of getting at
this is a different way than we've seen
it before
with a minimization of free
action
but let's return to
this page
and think about
how we can
distinguish with like a venn diagram or
something that helps us understand how
these core ideas are linked
one couple
that we can highlight is predictive
coding and predictive processing do you
have any thoughts or questions on that
yeah so maybe not a
venn diagram but like maybe we should
build
perhaps like a pyramid or like a
multi-level building because i think um
you know based on the
the
um what i read in the paper i think
really predictive coding
kind of starts it all off and also um
it makes sense to make a layer cake like
being that these all kind of start off
with the layers of um
cortical processing that happen quite
literally in the brain so i i think um
making a layer cake maybe makes the most
sense
okay so we're in the kitchen
we're in um the active restaurant
kitchen
and
what are we gonna
build in or what is the bottom of this
layer cake
so i think the bottom at least um
so so there might be two layers on the
bottom um
one from
helmholtz
so we can start with like the the
perception as unconscious inference view
of helmholtz
um and then predictive coding um as
described by rao and ballard
um in their
description of the visual system in the
visual cortex
okay and
again kind of calling back to the
dot zero
the
uh two qualitative philosophical ideas
that the authors invoke and that maria
helped us unpack
were helmholtz's notion of perception as
unconscious inference
and kant's
const notion that a priori or beforehand
structure like prior structure is needed
to make sense of sensory data
so we're gonna have one
um
bottom layer of the cake
with uh helmholtz
and then also with uh the kantian so
this is going to be our qualitative
philosophical
layer of the cake these two notions
and then you mentioned another critical
work which was round ballard's 1999 work
building on a broader history of
applying predictive and anticipatory
approaches to different neural systems
and in the dot zero the two neural
systems that we looked at were first the
retina system
with a
srinivasan 1982 and this is looking at
retinal
physiology and like the
electrophysiology of photons hitting the
retina
and then another area where predictive
approaches
especially early on
were getting built out around and
towards
was the cortical
hierarchy
and the different layers in the
mammalian cortex so these two anatomical
exemplars
of some
micro
circuitry some histology
that is compatible with
a predictive approach okay so we have
these two
basal layers but we might even add more
basal layers but we have
biological systems
that are doing predictive things
and that includes the
retinal as well as the cortex
also of course if anyone has like
questions we'll get to it in the right
way so please ask any questions or
doing any comments so we have the retina
the cortex
as examples but there's others
okay and then if there's a third layer
that
we can add to the bottom i think it
would just be bayesian statistics
because so
i think it comes maybe before that also
or maybe like maybe now
um
maybe bayesian statistics is like a
a layer two but like i think before the
bayesian statistics um and even before
biological systems doing prediction
there's the information theory component
that i think is
important also
okay
so well we have um this is qualitative
and philosophical
then we have
biological
and actual
and then we have a formal
area and that'll be
information and base
information
yeah the information goes under the bays
i think just like um the helmholtz comes
under
the cont right um i i think
it's the really the relationship between
um information and probability
which we started to
explore in um or we explored a lot in
the uh
fep of generic quantum systems
live stream number 40 that was 40 i
think
so many streams ago
okay
this is
fun and i think we're we're going to
start building this
into a tasty structure so we have the
philosophical
coming in on the left and that's one
on-ramp that
just like
we had discussed earlier like this is
something that has been almost
imminently available
to thinkers for thousands of years these
are the kinds of qualitative claims that
anyone can experience whether by
thinking about the blind spot or about
how their sense making in response to
some stimuli this is just the idea that
the sensory observations
are first off not the direct contact
with the world like we're not seeing the
lightning strike event we're seeing
photons hit the retina and sound hit the
eardrum and so we're receiving sensory
input that's that kind of plato's cave
angle
and then kant and helmholtz elaborated
on that to include this idea of
unconscious inference that requires a
priority structure or like what we would
call like a bayesian prior
then we have this biological area
and these are just reflecting natural
systems that are exhibiting some kind of
behavior like we can think about the
1999 paper of round ballard themselves
about the functional interpretation of
extra classical receptive field effects
and we talked about that in the dot zero
like the classical effects are kind of
the simple normative ones like the joke
is it's classical because of the papers
in the order they were published but
that doesn't like make it
even true let alone the best model the
classical is just like it's like classic
rock you might like other genres but
then there's the classics or whatever
so
that's the biological systems that are
exhibiting certain kinds of outcomes
and then we have these two
formal or quantitative areas
and those are the bayesian statistics
and probability as well as information
theory
and they're
definitely linked as well but we'll just
leave them as kind of two
conjoined layers here
okay
now
where do we go from here
well isn't that the question
so maybe um
predictive coding and predictive
processing um and like really what's the
the
difference between these two i think
predictive coding came from neuroscience
so maybe that layers on top of the
biological
part the biological piece of the cake
and then predictive processing might go
on to the
quantitative
piece
awesome
yeah and it really is what maria
highlighted
and and drew out in the dot zero
which was
using a a quote from an andy clark
book and clark wrote that predictive
processing is not simply the use of the
data compression strategy known as
predictive coding so at least in this
take
predictive coding is like mp4 it's like
an encoding strategy which is also why
we connected it to frame differencing
and video encoding but predictive coding
is going to be something that's data
oriented and it's related to information
theory compression
information encapsulation
and then clark is writing predictive
processing is not simply that
and so
maria spoke to how another way to think
about the difference between predictive
coding and predictive processing is to
use coding for the formalisms and
implementations
and processing for the philosophical
understanding that prediction is the
basis of signal interpretation
as opposed to merely recognition or
descriptive models so if anyone has like
a thought on that then
you know put it in the live chat or come
get involved but let's work with that
delineation going forward so predictive
processing
is going to be um
somehow related to the formal or sorry
predictive coding
is going to be more close to the formal
whether it's
predictive coding in a biological
context or whether it's going to be in a
philosophical context or something it's
going to be more on the formal side
whereas predictive processing
is going to be
where
a little bit closer to the philosophical
yeah i think so and then maybe like
does the bayesian brain like make up the
the third part of our like predictive
coding layers over the bayesian
statistics
and predictive processing layers over
the philosophical then does the bayesian
brain somehow make the in-between
sandwich that goes over the biological
okay
okay so let's see
we have
predictive processing
as being a philosophical approach
and consideration
of these
philosophical
memes and themes
in the biological case
which were
certainly bound to then
we can have predictive coding
as kind of the formal way
that these predictive anticipatory
systems
are implementing predictive processing
and then
what is the bayesian brain seems pretty
fair to put it at like the intersection
between
bayesian
and brain but what is the bayesian brain
to you
so to me the the bayesian brain is kind
of um
you know i i'm trying to look back
through the paper to their uh
description but um
in my like recollection recollection of
the bayesian brain which was like
probably my first introduction to
bayesian statistics i was like oh this
is great um and it wasn't even the
bayesian brain it was like the janesian
interpretation
of the bayesian brain paper but like
that paper was like probably the my
like turn on to bayesian statistics and
and implementing this and um
so so in my mind the bayesian brain is
is just this idea that
the brain
uses bayesian
reasoning or bayesian updating to
process information and and go forward
so but that's probably a very simplified
interpretation
i think there's going to be one
more realist interpretation like the
brain is doing bayesian stuff
and then there's the more
instrumentalist interpretation
we can use bayesian statistics to model
what it is that the brain is doing so is
bayesian
the territory or the map of the brain
but we'll just leave it as an edge for
now
so i'll read a question
from dean and then i think we're going
to be
exploring a lot where action
and active inference comes into play so
blue
dean writes
what do you think of this
as coding you are doing something in
coding
as processing
you determine by comparing
processing and or not processing as
you're doing
so process entails processing types
what
i'm hearing there is encoding
doesn't require two arguments
it just takes one you take one file and
you zip it you've encoded that in a
way
so
predictive coding
can
encode and or implement some type of
informational algorithm without a
reference or a comparator
whereas
dean's saying as processing
you determine
not with this
single argument
um plug and chug but you determine by
comparing
as you're doing and so predictive
processing
it it does have that sort of
top down and bottom up as it's often
visually represented but processing is
entailing that full stack
and therefore the processing is
requiring something like a minimum of
two to have consideration if you're
processing
nuts
then you're sorting them into two
different kinds or you're removing
something from something else about
those like you're doing something that
has
compositionality
or
some type of multiplicity to it it's not
just something you can take
that one file and just zip it so that's
a great point dean i think i'll add two
little arrows um
here
yes okay yes blue let me share the
slides
thank you
um i'm left in the dark here
uh i definitely um
yeah agree with dean's point about the
um coding versus processing like
i can
write a whole lot of things right like i
can take a whole lot of notes and that's
coding that's like encoding the
information from our conversation this
live stream but like until i do
something with those notes like turn
them into
elements of a paper that i want to write
or or something like this like i have
not processed what i have encoded until
i take them forward
to a forward step so i think like there
is kind of this temporal implication
with processing versus coding
yeah also like the timeliness of
processing like you want to process the
food before it has
become
you know bad or something so okay we
have
predictive coding again these are just
tentative slide play if anyone thinks
differently they can join or write a
comment but
predictive coding might entail
something of a unique directionality
just like a dot zip and you say well
somebody will unzip it later but we can
encode it
without that part of the loop being
required and then we have this two
directional relationship with predictive
processing being like
top down and bottom up um
[Music]
okay what do you see now or i can bring
up something
um yeah
so i'm not really seeing anything so why
don't you bring up what what is on your
mind or what what you're thinking of
where is action
and then i think that'll start to walk
us towards where active inference is
so because of the the temporal nature of
processing i think action might start in
the processing
um
element like even in something like
mental action like people do like
thought correction or thought
remediation
um so like if you're uh
you know you have this prediction
and it like surfaces in your mind but
then like you correct the prediction or
like you um
you know you think you see a snake on
the floor and then you say oh that's a
snake but then like you look
let me see that snake like and then you
have to zoom in look at it closer and it
ends up being like a coiled up rope
right and so it's not really a snake but
like you direct your attention because
of some prediction and then can continue
to process that prediction so so
possibly action starts in the processing
um
[Music]
in the processing area
or maybe it's there in the middle well
i'm gonna start it in the middle we can
see where it goes because i think it's
going to have an important edge
to each of these three areas so
there's a few ways to represent it of
course
so
how does
action relate to biological
systems or first let's let's um
start with some philosophical frameworks
that highlight the importance of action
so this includes
an activism
embodied
the four e's five e's seventies et
cetera et cetera et cetera everything
involving like
this sort of embodied enacted and
cultured extended etc approach to
cognition
and philosophy
and those can be qualitative so i'm
putting that edge here these are
different qualitative and philosophical
areas
yes they can be formalized we'll get to
that edge but these are qualitative
memes
that come from this philosophical area
and they're going to draw us to action
okay now
how about biological systems and action
what do you think about when you think
of biology and action
i don't know i think like those things
are kind of extra inextricably linked
in my mind um because like you can't
have life without
having some action i mean
cells replicate
yeah
i think this is going to be just uh
something that
doesn't
demand to be fed but is totally true
biological systems are active there it's
active matter
and life is this multi-scale
organization of activity
so
there's many ways biological systems are
doing action
and what are some areas that are formal
whether or not they have to do with
biology or any philosophy
can you name a few areas of like formal
theory and science that you think relate
to action
so i mean i think um just that's maybe
more related to processing um but but as
i said earlier i think processing is
related to action but like bayesian
inference and and variational inference
i think um
which also tie in a lot to active
inference um i i think that they come in
their
uh
in the processing slash
processing through action or action
through processing
okay
great so
um bayesian
planning as inference
as well as areas like cybernetics
control theory and
different formal ways
of modeling
active systems and modeling decision
making
these could be
related to a biological system or not
and they can be drawing on a
philosophical framework implicitly
explicitly or not
all right
so now this is starting to get fun you
added another
term there and i think this will merit a
detour but then i return to here which
is the variational bayesian approach
so
what do you think
variational
is meaning or doing here
so it's interesting and
part of what uh makes this complicated
um
paper and also like a complicated detour
that like the authors cast predictive
coding as variational inference like
even though we've kind of made this
distinction between predictive coding
and predictive processing
where coding does just is like a one-way
street and processing is like a two-way
street
um the authors nevertheless use the term
predictive coding as variational
inference
um and and this predictive coding
um
or this variational inference um i think
the the key
um construct here and that's probably i
don't know it overlaps with with
bayesian brain maybe two is the
idea of having a model of of the data
generating process and so
i think um variational inference kind of
throws the idea of a of a model into the
loop
okay
so let's zoom in on this blue
corner
of formal and quantitative areas
and so these can be taken in an action
independent way
they can be explicitly about action
like planning as inference
or they could just more implicitly rest
on inference i'm sorry more implicitly
rest upon action for example in the case
of we're inferring the hidden state of
the temperature of the room and we're
observing the thermometer that doesn't
have pi it doesn't have a it doesn't
have action in that model it might just
have those two parameters of like the
room's temperature hidden state and the
observations of the thermometer but then
we can kind of take a step back and see
all right well there's the person who's
engaging in this experimental action the
person's ocular motor
zooming in on the thermometer maybe we
can just abstract away but action is
always baked into it because we're
talking about active systems but let's
just put some of that aside for a second
and take a quick detour to talk about
variational inference because it's a
really important topic
let's think about and we've also
explored this in
active livestream 26
and 37 and a lot of other times so
let's look at three different ways of
doing bays
base ways
bayes areas as they were
so
and maybe there are more
but the three that we can list up here
are exact base
monte carlo
and variational base so pick one and
then what is like something important to
know about that way of doing bayesian
statistics
um well so
i'm by no means an expert in bayesian
statistics actually like cracked out my
bayesian data analysis book while i was
reading this paper because it was uh one
of those papers like i said i'm uh i'm
anal retentive and and detailed and i
love like what does that mean i have to
look up every little thing i don't
understand um so
like okay so let me start with the exact
ways um so exact base when i think about
exact base
it's like um
the probability of a given b like the
probability of rain given clouds or
something like that um and so
it's like a an alternate
alternative to frequentest statistics
where
um
[Music]
the probability of rain
and the probability of clouds or or like
a coin flip is easier to talk about
right like so each flip of the coin
is half and so like you know the idea
that what what are the chances that
you're gonna get heads
um
you know
five times in a row is half times half
times half times half times half so
um
in bayesian statistics there's um
or the probability that you're going to
get rain here this is it in frequency
statistics the probability that you're
going to get rain and the probability
that you're going to get clouds
is um the probability of rain times the
probability of clouds that's a great way
to put it and then in bayesian
statistics there's it evaluates the
probability of rain with clouds like
given what you already have observed
before like if it's rained it it's
usually cloudy this percent of the time
um and it takes into consideration the
probability of
rain with clouds probability of rain
probability of clouds all those things
separately so it gives you a prior
estimation i think
so i don't know that's probably super
confusing
great no you mentioned a lot of really
important points which is it's
uh
an alternative to frequentist statistics
analysis so we're not getting a p-value
out of this
and we're able to explicitly
say our priors
and
not to go down this rabbit hole but a
lot of frequentism implicitly has a
uniform prior and we'll just leave it at
that for now so the exact base is using
the bayes equation
essentially as written and just as you
said it there's the probability of
something given something else and then
you kind of find the probability of that
other thing given the first thing
multiplied by these other terms and then
you fill out all of those variables and
you literally do that division and so we
explored like this in the case of axel
constance paper with the bacteria and so
there was the exact bayesian bacteria
that was having its prior and then
taking in new information and updating
how it thought about what was out there
based upon the new incoming information
and it was like in a formula and it was
like dividing exactly the numbers that
you see here in this way
okay so that's exact base now
what are some issues with exact base
it might be straightforward when you're
talking about that coin flip but if
you're talking about a high dimensional
space
or something that is just bigger than
the ram or whatever of your computer
when it comes to the implementation
there's often challenges with exact base
and so there's several
techniques that have been developed
to
approximate
what an exact bayesian approach would be
in a more tractable way so there's two
alternatives to exact bay's
implementation and the spirit is going
to be exactly the same of taking in new
information and updating our priors as
specified but it's going to be done in a
few different ways so first what about
monte carlo what is monte carlo
um so monte carlo uh you probably know
more about the history than i do but but
um monte carlo is like a sampling
technique so you know instead of um
trying to calculate
the probability of um
rain and clouds using exact space
you just sample like out of you know
a thousand rainy days how many of them
were cloudy and out of you know a
thousand cloudy days how many of them
were rainy and so instead of like
getting an exact measurement of your
distribution like what is where is the
overlap between clouds and rain you just
randomly pick out from all of the
possible days
you estimate your sample
that way
great
so
it's based upon sampling
and so it's like
we might not know one of these terms but
we can at least draw a sample and so
this does a few different things it
connects us first to empirical and
specific data as implemented like in a
row of a program not just
b sub i or some sort of analytical
representation but like this is where
we're getting into this specific sample
was pulled by this algorithm at this
time
and
one method that's a common
thing is the markov chain monte carlo
and this is using a local resampling
approach like assessing local maneuvers
of a given chain that's engaged in
sampling and you kind of drop these
chains into different parts of the
probability distribution and then have
them evaluate different aspects of that
distribution so it's as easy or hard as
dropping those paratroopers
into different parts of the physical
landscape and then having them accept or
reject different proposed moves so
that's sort of a
two-dimensional landscape with the
height being elevation and maybe that's
what you want to map because you might
want to know is there one
central peak are there two peaks that
are very similar
and
take that into the statistical case
and this is especially helpful for when
there's no
um well i don't say no idea but there is
not the desire to explicitly formalize
what shape
the distribution looks like so we might
want to do like bayesian phylogenetics
and so we need to talk somehow about the
likelihood of a given dna sequence being
that way but like
where do you go from there
and so that's where the monte carlo
sampling based approach really comes
into play and then
because it's based upon sampling the
advantages are you can run that sampling
for three iterations or three million so
it's very flexible with the amount of
computing power that you bring to bear
on this
challenge
but also there are the risks of over
sampling which is that you have
used some unneeded electrical power and
computational power which is really
non-trivial but also there's the risk of
under sampling
and you might even be like in a regime
where you think that you've sampled
because you're
getting samples that are just confirming
what you already know
but you know there's a whole other
island that you didn't do the paradrop
to so
one can be lulled into a false precision
with bootstrapping and sampling based
approaches
because they can give ultra high
precisions
but that can be based upon um actually
more like a biased sampling approach or
all these other features and just the
one anecdote that i have on that is in
the
bayesian phylogenetics case
i remember this one professor in
undergrad uh professor moore and he'd
always say fuzzy caterpillar you want it
to look like a fuzzy caterpillar and
there's some technical details but it's
like you want it to be
exploring the full range
of a parameter like if something could
be zero to one you want to be exploring
the full range
but returning to the best estimate and
that shows that you're sampling like the
diversity of what that parameter can be
but also spending more or most of your
time
in the most likely and in the best
regions and so if the value were at
point five and the range of what's
possible was like zero to one that looks
like a fuzzy caterpillar with more
thickness in the middle and then a lot
of fluctuation but it's not like it's
spending a ton of time at one and then
it drops suddenly to zero because that
would suggest that you're not converged
yet whereas when you see that fuzzy
caterpillar it's like you're sampling
the extremes and getting novelty
and testing different combinations but
you're also returning to something that
is working so
monte carlo sampling based approach
brings in all these opportunities and
challenges associated with sampling
uh well so i i was under the impression
like you talked about over sampling but
i think um
[Music]
over sampling like as you as sampling
goes to infinity like your um
your accuracy increases like you're
you're more closer able to get the true
posterior um but i think it's it's
uneven sampling that's the the danger in
the monte carlo method like if you're
sampling too far in one end or the other
and perhaps like asymptotically if you
exhausted the state space
then you would know that you had the
right answer but the whole reason why
we're using any kind of heuristic
approach rather than exact base is
because like we don't have the full
state space so yeah there's um
relatively low cost to over sampling
but we don't always know when that is
and then under sampling can be just
totally
misleading if we take that as our only
um
representation of that distribution and
so there's all kinds of cool techniques
that involve like multiple chains
happening in parallel and some of them
are like higher temperature and less
temperature so for one of those
paratrooper teams
it's very cold and so they're only
making the best very local moves it's
like the elevation is sharpened for them
it's very hard to get out of a local
rut and there might be another team
that's very high temperature and for
them the landscape is flat
maybe even completely flat and then
they're like a hot molecule that's able
to move over something that might be a
barrier for another team so that team is
going to like fill in the details and
locally explore quality solutions
whereas there's another team that's like
or another chain and so that's the
multiple chain
monte carlo approach and there's a lot
to that in phylogenetics which is where
i've seen it the most but also probably
many other areas okay i've i've run it
in phylogenetics too and like i mean the
programs can take
forever
that's too fun because you know i mean
you're too many parameters and and
whatever they can really take a long
time um the computational power is no
joke like what goes into um the monte
carlo sampling so we have exact base
which is calculating the true posterior
and then we have the monte carlo which
is estimating the true posterior through
sampling and then we come to the
variational which is
trying to minimize the divergence
between
the true posterior and your
approximation of the posterior
great
minimizing divergence between
the true posterior
like what we would really have wanted to
actually know
what is the actual temperature in the
room conditioned upon the noisy
thermometer estimates that we're getting
so are we going to sample our way out of
that one
the variational approach is going to be
very different and and in 26 i think we
had like the cat
and then one approach was like the monte
carlo was like pointillism it was like
dots so we're sampling pixels from the
cat and then it becomes like a pointless
picture of a cat that if you do sample
densely enough it looks like a cat or
it's recognizable as a cat
and the variational approach was like a
clip art template and so let's just say
that you had a template of different
curves or of like you knew that
that it wanted to be a cat you knew you
were looking at a cat so then you have
like a cat
template that can get
stretched
or zoomed in or out
and so that might be very
straightforward to optimize
because you're just trying to minimize
the divergence between these very
limited parametric changes
that you can implement
but then of course you run into a
situation which will explore various
aspects of variational inference
what if you try to stretch
that cat emoji
onto
a different animal or what if it's a
totally different kind of data set so
you will
find some divergence minimizing solution
that doesn't mean it's sufficient or
even in the right ballpark just like
doing
l2 least squares minimizing
linear regression
will always find a best fitting linear
regression
but
that best fitting linear regression
can be like hilariously inaccurate like
if the data are like a uh a parabola
like a u
the best fitting regression might be
like a flat line through the middle or
if eighty percent of the points are here
and 20 are over here there might be a
regression that's very misleading that's
like the simpsons so-called paradox so
in variational we're not going to use
sampling we're going to use the
minimization of a divergence which is a
kl divergence but they mention in this
paper it can also be
a different kind of divergence and the
rainy divergence has been explored in
some recent work of sagitta at all so
we're going to minimize the divergence
between the true posterior
and a distribution queue
that we control and
is
tractable to optimize
so it's like instead of that sampling
based approach we were dropping the
teams at different parts of the
landscape
and then they were going to report back
on information here in the variational
approach it's like
we have a template
and then we're gonna just do stretching
and bending
again this is kind of a torture metaphor
but we're gonna stretch and bend and
there's only a few parameters on the
stretching and bending and we're going
to find the best
fit of those stretching and bending
parameters like if it were a linear
regression
y equals mx plus b
the two dials that you get to change are
like the m the slope of x and b like how
high or low the regression is and then
you're finding m and b
that are the best fitting
about the data y and so you're kind of
like minimizing the least squares
error term
here
it's not a linear regression that we're
fitting
by minimizing the least squares
it's a variational bayesian
approximation that we're fitting
by minimizing the divergence between the
true posterior and the distribution
queue that we control and is optimal or
is able to be optimized
what else would you add on that
um i think that's it so uh the the true
posterior and the the distribution
that is
tractable and
we can optimize over yeah that's it
so let's close this little okay
computational intensity on variational
is um
like much less
right than um
because instead of
calculating
all of the parameters for every little
dot every little point on the sample
we are calculating
for like a big blob
it's like one big blob instead of
several little points but we calculate
for that big blob this is the density of
that of that function
um and these are the parameters of that
so so now we're gonna
back out of this formal cul-de-sac that
we've been in and just remember to
ourselves even if it's your first time
hearing variational inference
and or you're kind of like blue or eye
where it's like we've read it in how
many papers but still every time we kind
of start on square zero so why do we use
variational bayesian inference so the
first thing is it allows us to use
bayesian statistics and probability
which we might prefer over for example
frequentism okay variational bayes then
allows us to use a heuristic bayesian
implementation
so if there's something that's too
challenging or implausible for exact
base
now we can approach it
like monte carlo or variational these
are both heuristics
unlike monte carlo it's not based upon
sampling variational is based upon a
family of equation fitting and so it can
be implemented very efficiently which
isn't always the case for monte carlo it
rests upon an appropriate factorization
of the problem
and one other piece is this connects
to
analytical equations in physics
so it's almost like monte carlo is like
a computer scientist's approach
it's like how much ram do we have how
many processors do we have how big is
this data set going to be and then
there's no analytical
equation or closed form for monte carlo
it's like engineering it's kind of like
you have to have some art and skill and
science coming together for the monte
carlo to be the best it can be
and then it's more about like an
adequacy and an efficacy question
because you're not converging to the
infinite asymptote again otherwise you
could have done something else and then
the variational is like the physicist's
approach and it draws on the variational
calculus of feynman and others and this
is the part that's very amenable and
connected to the equations of least
action and all these other things like
factorizing equations
so it's funny that you bring up the
computer scientist approach um
in monte carlo and like so
[Music]
i am a horrible
computer person i mean i will brute
force wrangle my data like just give me
more ram just give me more processing
power like i i um i just want to make
things work
i don't have any patience for
finesse right so in my mind i think
about the monte carlo like the brute
force just shove your data through the
algorithm no matter how much ram it
takes i think about monte carlo like
that and i think about um
the variational bays more like the
people that
can do like
you know very simple things in code to
make it run much faster that have that
like very good skill with like oh well
we can just you know run this little
factorization or or um
you know we can make the problem run so
much better on the computer
so i think about it about the
variational um like that but you're
right it does have that connection to
statistical physics and to definement
but i think about it as like a highly
optimized
way to run bayesian statistics but why
daniel would someone want to run
bayesian statistics in the first place
so so maybe you want to give us an
example why why would that happen well
yeah we will pull back just the last
point there is
the variational methods we might even
have a heuristic for those or an
algorithm or approximation of those for
example message passing and forney
factor graphs
those draw an equivalence between bayes
graphs where nodes are random variables
and edges are statistical relationships
bayes graphs
can undergo variational inference
and there's a tractable way to use
toolkits like that developed by the bias
lab
and use message passing and a 40 factor
graph representation to have like a
level of implementability for even the
variational whereas it's not possible to
imagine like a heuristic for monte carlo
it is the heuristic sampling is sampling
you can do better sampling but that's
the game that you have chosen whereas in
variational even this question of
minimizing divergence does require kind
of like a
proximate or an operational approach
because how can we minimize the
divergence between the true posterior
and something we control when we don't
know what the true posterior is so there
have to be a little bit
more added but this is like very
awesome discussion because it's helping
us pull out like this is the sort of
exact approach and then there's a more
computer science like sampling approach
and then a more analytical and
physics-related approach okay
so why do we want to do base let's
pull back
to our
triangle here
why do we want to do base and thinking
about the concepts here why do we want
to do base
i asked you you're not allowed to turn
the question around on me that was me
asking you you're not allowed to just
talk and then ask me
[Music]
well there's a few ways to take it i
guess one would be
what is the alternative policy selection
if we're doing research or application
what is our our alternative to picking
some bayesian approach so if we take the
bayesian road we know that there's going
to be some sort of
trivergence later exact base monte carlo
variational base something else
or we could go down a different
statistical path like we could use
frequent
statistics
and maybe that's totally adequate and
effective for the situation
and both are just maps so a well-fitting
linear model
of height and weight doesn't make height
and weight a linear model
a really good fitting action perception
loop whether it rests upon a kernel of
frequency statistics or bayesian
statistics doesn't make those systems
that way that you modeled it
um so i would say bayesian statistics is
useful when we want to do
some kind of
formal or quantitative inference
where we want to be
specific and explicit
about our prior beliefs
and how we want incoming information to
update those beliefs
so i i agree and um
it's what i always try to tell people um
you know when i'm explaining like what
is bayesian statistics which a lot of
people have never heard of um like in
college at least when i graduated
there's not there's no bayesian
statistics course now many schools have
them um and you know i'm outdated
already but uh
it's really like when you're doing
frequented statistics
you go out to the desert and count mice
every year right every year you go and
count how many mice you see in the in
the desert or something like this
and
if you i mean you expect to see some
mice in the desert otherwise you
wouldn't be there counting them so um
you expect a non-zero
answer right so every year you go out
you find 10 mice 20 mice 50 minus 30
mice 20 mice 10 mice and every year you
go count mice so
if you were to go like you have some
expectation that you will find mice um
you also have some expectation that
there is going to be less than a
thousand mice because every year you can
sample this one place right and so um
what bayesian statistics does is it
takes actually that prior not like
frequent statistics they don't care if
you ever found mice there before like
your probability of finding zero mice
and 30 mice and 50 mice and 100 mice and
a thousand mice is all the same it
doesn't matter how many years you've
been there before like you are starting
with nothing in frequent statistics you
don't get to have any guess that there's
even going to be one mouse in the desert
where with bayesian
statistics like obviously you think that
there are there are going to be some
mice and you think it's going to be some
number you can count reasonably so with
whatever area and so what bayesian
statistics statistics allows for is that
prior belief or that expectation that
you have as experimenter
awesome and that's kind of
what we were getting at with that idea
of frequentism having this implicit
uniform distribution you flip the coin
ten times you get three heads
your maximum likelihood estimate is it
comes up 30 of the time on heads 0.3
however if you want to take like a
bigger picture of you you might have
some sort of precision about where it's
likely to be like is it
likely to be 0.5 and you're going to be
surprised if it were 0.3 because you
just pulled it out of
a cash register and then in that case
you still might say i want to have a
uniform prior and if it is 0.3 then it's
0.3 or you might want to say i'm very
confident it's something else but
bayesian statistics opens up the space
to be specific about how we want to use
our priors how confident we want to be
how much precision we want to have in
those priors and then how we want to
incorporate new information so any other
thought on that or let's continue on
that and connect it to some formalisms
so i have one more thought on the coin
flip with baby with the bayesian idea
like if you know it's a fair coin and
the probability is 50
and like if you're we're flipping coins
and we're betting each time like you
know a dollar a dollar a dollar if if we
flipped that coin you flip the coin
10 times in a row in its heads every
single time like on the 11th time like
my bet is on tails because like it's not
it's a fair point like it's not going to
come up
um every single time heads and so
frequent to statistics like does never
allow for that previous information and
also like where is that information
which is something that always baffles
me like does the coin already know that
it's been flipped ten times and it's
come up heads all those times and that
it then has to come up tails sooner or
later i mean that the probability is so
low that you're gonna get like a
thousand coin flips of a fair coin in a
row that is heads like i don't know if
it's ever happened to anyone ever so
like as we increase in the number of
flips and if it's heads heads headsets
heads like it becomes increasingly
probable that the next flip is going to
be tails in my view right which is maybe
totally wrong but but where is that
information stored and um the bayesian
kind of prayer allows for that to be
there
and i wonder if this even connects to
where is that information stored
in the quantum reference frame of the
observer and nowhere else but
let's look at how that gets implemented
in these formalisms so you just describe
that setting where somebody has like a
belief that the coin is fair maybe
that's an empirically grounded belief
like previously they flipped it a
thousand times and they got 50 50.
or they have just an a priori
belief that is fair if that belief were
generated by a real other data set we
would call that parametric empirical
base because it's the process where you
set the priors
as well as their confidence based upon
some collected data set
that's parametric empirical base
or one could just take that a priori
cons
synthetic a priori
and just say coins ought to be
50 50 and that's what i'm sticking with
let's just say that then we play this
game we flip it 10 times and
likely or not
10 heads
happen that's the trace of behavior in
the niche it actually happened now that
might be seen as a totally likely
outcome by somebody who believes that it
always comes up heads hence they're
unsurprised or depending on what your
priors were that could be variably
surprising and then you
talked about well when and how should
you update
your beliefs on that coin
like maybe something changed while you
weren't looking at it and so you want
like your best estimate
to very heavily reflect the recency and
maybe that should be like a moving
average of the most recent
three flips or maybe the most recent 30.
so let's look at two places in the paper
where they do something like that
the first one has to do with
predictive coding
and frame differencing algorithms in
video compression
and so
in this
area
we can think about
the
way that the video
looks
people who are watching this video the
way that the video looks is like the
output and then we want to encode like
how surprised are we what is happening
when the frames are changing and so the
simplest method is just count where it's
different
and convey that information
but it might also be important to use as
they write
more advanced methods that predict each
new frame
using a number of past frames weighted
by a coefficient in approach known as
linear predictive coding
so that's one case where you're
determining how many frames back how
many coin flips back
should we use for that now casting
and how should we weight them
so that's one area
and then a second area that they bring
up and connect
is the calm and filter
so here's the common filter and this is
their formalisms 33 and 34.
and it has a lot to do with bayesian
statistics so on this and bayesian
column filter is very common
we can see it in two different ways so
on the left side of this slide
the top image
shows um a prior prediction that's the
prediction and then two is the
measurements and then there's the fusion
so we have the prediction the
measurement here with like gps and then
there's the fusion
so that is very similar to having a
prior and then some updated sensory
information and then the posterior so
it's just labeled slightly differently
but we can already see how this is like
totally related to bayesian statistics
what this also brings into the picture
is like a pseudo code that unrolls
through time
so a bayesian statistics approach
doesn't have to be about time it can be
about a static data set
and then you could be modeling like okay
per extra sample of the population of
their height and weight we're going to
update our inference on that
relationship
but that's a timeless analysis it
doesn't incorporate some sort of
unfolding through time
that can be incorporated into the kalman
filter
using this pseudo code down here on the
left there's some prior knowledge of
state and this is like two dimensions
and then there's a cloud representing a
distribution of precision or uncertainty
so a more precise estimate would be like
a tighter cloud there or a sharper peak
or a sharper valley depending on how you
want to think about it
and then less precision
would be like a broader basin or like a
more diffuse ink drop and then
there's a prediction
then a measurement occurs which can be
precise or can also have an associated
measurement error term
which could be fit with parametric
empirical bays based upon testing or it
could be determined on the fly with
expectation maximization and then that
prior gets juxtaposed in this update
step
and that outputs
so this takes sort of this timeless
bayesian update scheme
and specifically adapts it to the case
of something happening through time
and that's shown on the right side here
with this image of like time is
happening
and we're getting these noisy x
measurements
and the true temperatures the purple and
let's just say it's unchanging in this
case but that could also be changing one
can just imagine that especially if it's
very noisy
it's hard to get
increasingly complex dynamical patterns
but
that's all part of the game
and then the prior starts high
and then the prior
is weighted it's kind of like a spline
it's weighted
through all of these x's and you can
imagine one extreme case is like
move to the last one that you saw
and so that would be like basically
recapitulating the measurement
distribution through time
the other extreme case would be
wait all the time points evenly so that
like we're kind of converging to a
moving average so if we have a hundred
hours of video that is like at a two
and then all of a sudden it switches to
an eight
and then your moving average would very
very slowly
start moving up from a two
and then one could imagine that there's
some intermediate solution
that doesn't use like the whole data set
because that's too slow to adapt and
maybe takes up too much memory but isn't
just like a one step
instantly switch to the nearest
measurement and that parameter
of how fast should you update your
kalman filter
is a parameter in the model
and so that is exactly what is being
statistically optimized is
how much
through time
should we update our ongoing estimate
and so in the static or the timeless
bayesian case that's where we talk about
precision how much should we update our
inference as new information is added to
our data set but that doesn't mean
appended in a temporal way
the common filter is making it explicit
that these data points are being added
sequentially
and that is providing us with this
pseudo code by which the latent state
update the latent state
is updated
not just as a function of adding data
but actually adding data in a sequential
and unrolling way what do you think blue
yeah great i think that that was a super
good
explanation and
very clear and
yeah um
my first uh
interaction with common filtering was in
imaging and image processing and so i
think
that's maybe where people come across
that a lot especially like doing laser
scanning microscopy or
a video i guess the video update also is
like that so
yes so let's just look at some of their
um writing but these are like
the smaller the formalism
the less we've paid attention to it and
the more that we would love to know
about what it actually means but let's
kind of pick up above their 35 they
write
coleman filtering proceeds in two steps
first the state is projected forwards
using the dynamics model or prior and
that's the p
of mu t plus one that's the mean
at the next time step conditioned upon
the mean at this time step so that's
like
what is
going to happen next conditioned upon
how it is now
these estimates are corrected or sort of
compromised
coming to a compromise by new sensory
data by inverting the likelihood mapping
p
of observations at the next time point
conditioned upon our estimate of where
the latent state will be so this is what
temperature will the room be conditioned
upon how it is now
at the next time step what will it be
conditioned upon what it is now
this likelihood mapping which is like
the a matrix in the pomdps
is what is the probability of the
outcome in the next time step being a
certain way
conditioned upon
how we think the room's temperature is
going to be and so these are the
equations and some of the
variables
and then
they kind of conclude or in this little
section the derivation of the rules is
relatively involved and that's in
appendix a and some other places
but also the common filtering can be
interpreted as finding the optimum of a
maximum a posteriori estimation
problem
so this is almost like we have kant
with
the exhortation of the a priori what
information are we bringing to the table
qualitatively
can't
or
quantitatively bayes that's the a priori
and then baze kind of bridges the a
priori the prior with a posteriori
not sure if that's the latin for that
one but it's the posterior what happens
after the sensory update and then that
space between like the before
and the after
is the during
and that's the during of the now that
were doing action and inference within
let's look at how they introduce oh
anything otherwise we'll look at how
they introduce action and then connect
it back to active inference
so
i i think um
the common filtering and the the
updating so i think we we kind of
skipped over
um
updating when we were talking uh when we
were making our layer cake earlier
um and just how um
how messages in the nervous system
biologically and in predictive coding
are
passed forward and backwards so it might
be helpful to back up and talk about
error propagation and
propagation of
back propagation and propagation of
signal through time um just as like a
very
basic way because i think the common
filter
um is kind of an advanced way to do that
okay can we detour
we're back at the triangle and so now
we've added variational as like a little
badge
to um
the bayesian and also we're going to add
coleman as a badge where have we visited
on this journey and
one can imagine that they could take a a
monte carlo or a variational or an exact
approach to common filtering and so on
and then you mentioned a few more
biologically inspired or compatible
features
like error propagation and so on so what
is a area in the paper or an idea that's
relevant here
so i think
the the signal propagation and and
bottom-up
prediction error like how does error
propagate
like through
visual systems through like neural
networks i think that there's
applications here um
and is it the error that's fed forward
or is it the signal that's fed forward
or where does the error go in the system
so i think these are some some
confusing things that that maybe they
they touched on um
in
the beginning of the paper so let me see
if i can find exactly
um
or there's some debate okay i'm while
you're looking so i've i've
pulled out
this
right edge of the triangle so we're
going to just
leave some of the baggage at home
and take out to the table
just this link between
bayesian statistics and probability and
biological systems
and then you raise this really important
question about like how do we think
about error estimation
and also some related terms there would
be like
precision ambiguity
risk
compression
and that so that those are error
estimates
and then how are error estimates
propagated and communicated
how are they propagated and communicated
in language
i'm not sure
if i had to guess
in power error estimates communicated in
systems and so we might be interested in
mathematical systems
so then the way that you communicate the
error is just you multiply the two
variables you have a precision matrix
and then you have like some sort of
hidden state matrix and then you
basically just fuzz
this kind of pristine matrix
by some error matrix and so if your
error on something is like zero this is
not exactly how the multiplication would
work because multiplying by zero but
if the error were zero on something
one would want their estimate to be
passed through without being blurred
if the estimate of the uncertainty were
super high
in the extreme approaching total
noise and uncertainty and variance
estimate then no matter where that
pristine estimator were you'd want it to
be like totally fuzzed over and then one
could imagine that in a per variable
ongoing way
you'd want to be updating these variance
estimators and that is exactly what
happens in the common filter which is
this unrolling and ongoing estimate of
observations
latent states and
the the variance that links them and
that's done like through matrix
multiplication but how does it happen in
biological systems is a different
question
so i i think um
some things come into play here like um
redundancy
and signal compression and then error
propagation
forward and backward um and so there is
this um
in predictive coding
slash predictive processing because i'm
still like not 100
um on the on the difference there
but but i do think this is a predictive
um
it seems like that it's a predictive
processing uh thing but the authors do
say
predictive coding there is like a bottom
up
um
construction of a model
so the authors say that um
but it's not only that pers it's the
authors say that perception is not the
result of an unbiased feed forward or
bottom-up processing of sensory data but
is instead a process of using sensory
data to update predictions generated
internally by the brain
so there's
the idea of a model comes in here yeah
generative model where do you see
generative model
in these discussions
i mean it's kind of threaded throughout
so i think the the idea of um
variational inference
brings in a model because the model
constructs
the
um
estimate of the posterior like where
we're consistently there's a consistent
effort to update the estimate of the or
to sorry to minimize the divergence
between the actual posterior and the
estimate of the posterior
so the estimate of the posterior is like
you know trying to make the model match
reality so trying to make the picture of
the cat match
stretch bend fold into um
you know the model of the cat
yes awesome so generative model with no
complications is being put into the
bayesian statistics area because if you
specify a model that's generating
thermometer
outputs given the temperature it's quite
literally the generative model and we
know that there's kind of two directions
there's like the recognition model and
the generative model that's the tail of
two densities
because a
distribution can also be understood as a
density and so in the realm of
statistics generative model is quite
literally
the approach that is taking parameters
of a model and using it to generate for
example observations in this case
no need to complicate that but then
there's a few ways that we hear
different people in different papers
talking about the relationship between
biological systems and generative models
as well as recognition models but we're
focused on the generative model here and
sometimes these are even
coherently or incoherently used
differently in the same paper or the
same sentence
which is our favorite and will
eagerly await the kind of automated
detection systems that will enable us to
do
high throughput analysis but here's just
a few of the kind of ways that people
can talk about that
we hear sometimes that the biological
organism or cell
is a generative model
has a generative model
enacts a generative model or the more
instrumentalist
we can model
that system with a generative model
and so this bottom one
is kind of like saying
i'm just planning to use bayesian
statistics
to model a biological system
and perhaps we could say that this is
the least
bringing assumptions to the table
of what that system is doing because by
saying we can model it using a
generative model we can use or fit
derive a generative model for this
behavioral cognitive system
we're just
remaining purely with both feet in
scientific instrumentalism and
empiricism we're making only claims
about the map
and not about the territory per se which
might
be
throwing out the um
whatever with the whatever however
these ones are when people are making
claims
that are about the territory
what is the brain is bayesian brain what
the brain is doing well
it's not passing around screenshots of
bayes equation like we are so what is it
that it is doing
or again is it on the instrumental side
it's just something that we can use to
model the brain so
yeah
so um
going back to predictive coding and and
also linking to what is the brain um
doing and really this is why i wanted to
uh stop here um i found i found the spot
in the paper um but but when we were
talking about
common filtering and um
image uh
processing and then error propagation
in a system um they they talk early in
the paper about predictive coding
as a means to remove redundancy
uh and applied it to signal processing
to reduce transmission bandwidth for for
video
um
and this
they the authors say here
um
barlow apply applied this principle to
signaling in neural circuits arguing
that the brain faces considerable
evolutionary pressure for information
theoretic efficiency since neurons are
energetically costly and redundant
firing would be potentially wasteful and
damaging to an organism's evolutionary
fitness
because of this we should expect the
brain to utilize a highly optimized code
which is minimally redundant
and they say predictive coding minimizes
this redundancy by only transmitting
errors or residuals of sensory sensory
input that cannot be explained by
top-down predictions and so they remove
redundancy at every point in the layer
so it's like when you're watching a
video
and um or even like the flip book like
so we see like you know the the flip
book that likes of a little figure
kicking a ball
the point that changes is the point
that's prioritized the point that's
different in each frame not the point
that stays consistent because that is
where the action is here
where the motion is happening so that
that's what's prioritized here
and that
totally connects to information theory
informative updates are the ones that
update your
prior
to move it to a different posterior
that's the bayesian information
concept
as opposed to for example the
shannon entropy which is like based upon
symbol entropy so they're totally
compatible and if this seems like a
technical detail it is
but also this is the bayesian concept of
surprise and information but that was a
great section you pulled out so
here we're we're really highlighting as
following barlow
applying
this
principle of redundancy removal but
already we can caveat
how much redundancy to remove because a
more redundancy removed system is also
potentially more fragile
like if we only have one copy of each
saved file
now our
threat
of losing it is very high so redundancy
is always in a trade-off with like
resilience and other system features so
this is one principle but it's not the
only principle at play so redundancy
doesn't mean we're going to pare it down
to nothing
it just means that for
an organ like the brain
which is using like 20 percent or
however much of an organism's energy
budget
changes in its efficiency by several
percent can be really important so that
principle of redundancy removal is being
applied
and the argument is that the
evolutionary pressure
is for information theoretic efficiency
so if you don't have anything to update
you don't want to spend the energy to do
something extraneous nor do you want to
spend any more energy than you might
have to on updating
and that's again because of the
wastefulness of
potentially excess signaling
and then with evolution there's always a
twist like what if it is wasteful and
that's just
some second level reason why so it's not
the whole story this is just sort of
short sentences
because of this
we should expect the brain to utilize a
highly optimized neural signaling neural
firing code which is minimally redundant
and then they connect it back from what
the brain
ought to be doing normatively at a first
pass
to
the formalisms that were being described
with predictive coding
so in the frame differencing case
it was like
only tell me about the pixels that are
changing
and then if nothing's changing just send
me like a little beep and i'll just know
with just one piece of information just
to keep it exactly the same even if it's
4k video and it's a gigabyte per second
or whatever but we don't have to change
anything for that video and then
as pixels are changing
update me on how to change them
and so that would be like the
maximum efficiency encoding
and so you would give a full resolution
of the first frame in the movie that's
the prior that's d
and then all one has to do is think
about how to encode
how the subsequent frames change
and sometimes they introduce things like
a keyframe so every second or every
minute it's it starts with a fresh prior
and so these are the kind of
computational things that one can do
when they're not bound by like the
constraints of biological systems but
this is an awesome connection um
any other thoughts on that
um theme or like where does error
propagation come into play or we'll turn
back to the triangle
so i don't know the error of propagation
is is interesting it'd be great to have
like the input of somebody who um
is more like versed in machine learning
because i think
the idea of like back propagation like
this is an error and like sending that
back to the previous like layer in the
neural network is super interesting and
part of what um like enhances the
efficiency of neural networks like hey
fix this and so i think um and i can't
really find in the paper where they say
that but but there's like a local
correction for error within each layer
of processing so um in the visual system
and um
in signal processing itself it's like
each
layer prioritizes just fixing their own
error and then
that contributes to the overall
efficiency and um
uh accuracy of the system at large yes
back propagation is mentioned
45 times in the paper with a quick
search so it's definitely an important
concept and also something the authors
have worked in a lot
so good error propagation and back
propagation
and also that reminds me of um when
professor levin
was here in 40.2
with the back propaganda
and the imperatives for like the
different parts of the neural network
and the kind of information that they
want
or expect or prefer and then how they
want to escape being trained and engage
in learning but not being trained but
still updating
so it's learning and being trained both
involve like updating priors potentially
appropriately but in the case of
training there's a feeling like another
entity or agents
is
imposing their will
versus learning can also be associated
with um behavioral
and cognitive changes
but
has a different sense potentially than
being trained
anyways let's go back to the triangle
as we're sort of
not quite
landing the dot one play you know the
check has not arrived at our restaurant
but um maybe we're working our way up to
our first star
um where do we sit on where action
is and then we have a few terms that we
want to put which is message passing
and then active inference
oh yeah so what is another term that we
can add in
or something that we're seeing
differently in a new light
or where do you see message passing or
active inference
um
so i think
yeah
so
we have action are we happy with where
action is sitting
i've used every feature of google slides
sufficiently um i i like action as sort
of a fulcrum in the center of the
merry-go-round
is action and yes more arrows could be
drawn but we'll keep it a little sparse
but go ahead
so
i think
maybe
message passing sits between
predictive processing and action
and then that's exactly where i was
going to put active inference was right
where you just typed in inference
um because i think uh if we're or
yeah
it's hard to say um
where active inference really goes maybe
like
not right where inference is but like
somehow if action and the bayesian brain
and biological systems could form a
a triad maybe active inference would sit
in the middle of those
things
um
so i added message passing to bayesian
statistics and probability because it's
something that we can do on a bayesian
graph
it's a implementational approach but
it's also
leaning a little bit towards the
biological
because when people talk about like how
does a given piece of information or
signaling or stimulus in
the toe
end up having an effect on the other
side of the body or on the brain like
there's some kind of now it's being used
in a technical bayesian sense with
message passing
whereas in a more just sort of like
conversational way
um
with biological message passing but
whether it's a synapse
an immune synapse or a neural glial
synapse or it's a mechanotransduction
or a hormone
broadly we can just consider these
different biological mechanisms that
convey information or updates or
anything
to be like
past messages so message passing is
going to be a formal technique but it
does lean towards
modeling the ways in which different
biological nested entities are
exchanging information yeah
and so why i would put it with
predictive processing is because when i
think about the things that we were
talking about like
how are signals compressed how is
redundancy eliminated how is error
propagated through a system or back
propagated so
which is why like i liked it
there in the processing because like you
can't
legitimately process that information
without like knowing how the message is
going to be passed like if you're only
going to get every fourth letter
of the message i passed well i'm going
to encode my message in every fourth
letter not in every
single letter
and that changes right
okay thanks yes so we have message
passing
now
as part of the philosophical concept of
systems that engage in holistically
considered predictive processing because
it connects what biological systems are
are doing with some idea about like
information sharing without any
formalism but then message passing
via the forney factor graphs
is gonna be in the bayesian side because
that's like the implementation so maybe
message passing here yeah it's like on
the sort of predictive coding
implementational side whereas we don't
we're not saying biological systems are
doing for any factor graphs and message
passing in that technical sense but for
sure we can think about it in this
qualitative way okay
so we have action
in the sensor
and then kind of bifurcated it to
include action and inference
aka active inference
for a few reasons first off
action
is not just
blind
flailing action
when we talk about planning as inference
and inference on action
and inference about future latent states
and observations
that aren't explicitly about action but
we know an act of inference that they
actually do condition on action so
inference and action how we think and
how we act how the entity's cognitive
model is and how the entity's behavior
is through time
those two are like an inseparable duel
and that's why active inference
says it all in the title
it's about action and inference and all
of the ways that they are related to
each other again whether it's like
planning as inference about future
action
or inference on the consequences of
or
it's inference about something that
isn't explicitly action itself like what
is the temperature but it requires or is
conditioned upon
policy selection
in this framework not the only way to
look at it but that's how they come
together in active inference and like
let's peep over to 4.5
where they introduce action
formally
the basic approach to including action
within the predictive coding framework
is to simply minimize the variational
free energy with respect to action
free energy is not explicitly a function
of action
up until equation 51 it can be made so
implicitly by noticing the dependence of
sensory observations on action
so if your future sensory observations
don't depend on action or don't depend
on that kind of action
this is like an extraneous
calculation like if you have a coin flip
and you're rolling a dice
and they don't influence each other
then they're conditionally independent
and so there's no need to calculate the
joint distribution if you're just
interested in the coin flip because it's
not
having a causal relationship with the
rolling the die
however
if we're going to have agency
or model systems that appear to have
agency
then there's some kind of dependence
on future sensory observations related
to action
in the visual case
the visual input is conditioned upon the
ocular motor decisions and those are
actions of a musculoskeletal system
and then the way that it gets tucked
into the equations
is
the change in action with respect to
time
is going to be
related to a gradient so like a partial
differential equation but then it's
amenable to gradient descent it's going
to be like a partial
derivative
of free energy and how it changes with
respect to action
so like am i minimizing free energy by
steering the wheel more to the left or
by steering the wheel more to the right
that's like d f over d a
change in free energy over change in
action
and then free energy f here
is a function not just of the joint
distribution of o and mu
not just a joint distribution of the
observations on the thermometer
and the mean estimate of temperature in
the room
that's kind of the pure inference take
but again
we're suggesting that sensory
observations have a dependence
could be partial could be complete on
action and so now observations
themselves
are a function of action
and then that can be unpacked a little
bit more
in 51 and they discuss it further of
course in the paper and elsewhere but
that's like how this inferential
framework
gets built in predictive coding
and then action
becomes introduced
as something that inference can be about
and that's what they say
allows for predictive coding agents
to undertake adaptive actions without
any major change to their fundamental
algorithms
it's not like there was the
temperature thermometer module
and then now there's this totally ad hoc
decision making module that's bringing
in all this thing about what is the
reward of different temperatures what is
the reward of different thermometer
observations
rather within this same
parsimonious and first principles
inference framework we can model
active inference which is inference
including action
let's kind of continue on this action
theme and then we'll we'll end in a few
minutes
so under such a scheme
the prediction error
becomes the difference between the
current observation and the target or
set point
that raises the question of where these
set points and targets come from
and that's where they just sort of have
that road leading off into the distance
saying well in the evolutionary case
it's inherited
in the computational case it's just
simply there it could be just a priori
speculated or it could have been a
parametric empirical phase
so that's one really interesting point
is like when you do introduce action
you have to discuss not just the target
or the set point and how it's generated
but also you have to make explicit in
the forward model as they write the
dependence of the observations upon
action and that has to be provided or
learnt
because just that temperature
thermometer model
is not going to include a forward model
of what happens when you turn on the
heater or when you put on a jacket so
that's something that has to be learned
and then a second interesting thing that
starts to come out of their framing here
is like the costs of action and that
closes the loop really well with the
discussion that you raised of like
barlow
and the information efficiency argument
for why the brains ought to be doing
something
something like
predictive coding efficient signal
transfer
and hence why it's either what they
ought to or are doing
or and
how we ought to or could
model it
so that's why the costs of
this are important cost of action are
important
and then just one last piece in four or
five was active inference in the pid
control
which is related to the generalized
coordinates of motion and we
unpack that a lot in live stream number
26 with the bayesian mechanics paper of
decosta at all
and this connects
control in active inference systems to a
very commonly used engineering framework
for controlling processes which is pid
control
which is framing action through time as
being related to these three terms which
are described above
so
that's how they brought action into this
paper was by spending many of the early
sections
providing like the single layer
predictive coding model
and connecting that to variational bays
that was in like sections two
and then in section three
and also in section two they explored
all these different interesting
generalizations the spatial case the
hierarchical case and then they also
connected it to
biological systems and reviewed some
evidence for predictive coding of
different kinds
and then in section four
when they connect to several other
inference algorithms like predictive
coding and the back propagation of error
linear predictive coding and the kalman
filter
normalization and the normalizing flows
which we didn't talk about
predictive coding is biased competition
also something we didn't talk about and
then
after all that action gets tucked into
the picture and it's just like very
clean in a very elegant way
to think about it and helps us
understand like maybe even how active
inference is similar or different to
some of these other frameworks
so in the spirit of our layer cake i
think um today like we covered
if this paper is a sandwich
we covered both slices of bread
like the very beginning and the very end
but we left out like all of the things
that kind of come in between um the meat
and potatoes
have you had potatoes on a sandwich ever
they do it with some
french fries sometimes but i know what
you mean
go to subway i'm gonna go to subway and
be like yeah can i get some potatoes on
my on myself
did i have a predicting coding special
and then they go then they go what do
you expect is gonna be on this sandwich
it would be cool uh next week to really
kind of dive in um more to uh
error back back propagation predictions
are sent you know up and
errors sent down um or or is it the
other way around um
and really kind of discuss these these
computational graphs that they start to
talk about so i think next week would be
really cool to kind of dive into what's
inside of the of the sandwich oh awesome
okay so we'll definitely go into some
some so what's inside
the sandwich
um
a back propagation
of error
biological evidence and examples
so i think there's a ton of uh exciting
stuff that we'll be able to talk about
next week
um like the different paradigms like we
could cover over figure three the
paradigms of predictive coding and
um
the normalizing flows so we definitely
um we covered the bread today
uh yes
um
um well
anyone who is listening we really
appreciate it look forward to your
comments on the video or joining us next
week if that's gonna work
and
blue this was like
super
interesting and very helpful so i think
it's a great
dot one
and it's funny because like dot one it's
it's the meat and potatoes of the zero
one two
sandwich
so it's like
our middle of the bottom of the bathtub
phase the dot one where we're opening up
all these ideas and just trying to like
give a second coat of paint on a few
things go into a few technicalities
re-represent some knowledge it's like
that was
in a very
paradoxical or delightful way about
not the potatoes itself but rather about
the beginning and the end
well to be fair for those of you who
haven't yet read the paper there's like
60 equations and like 55 pages plus an
appendix
so
uh no surprise that we covered
the bread um but it would be cool to
tear apart a little bit of what's inside
of
the paper because i think that these
layers are cool and important and the
paradigms of predictive coding were
super interesting to me and i love like
the intersection between the brain
and machine learning and i learned a lot
um reading this paper especially like i
was taking neuroscience classes i'm
going to you know say how old i am right
now but i was taking like neuro in
college at like 12 at like in 2003
probably maybe 2004
um
with no idea learning about you know the
work of rao and ballard and hubel and
weasel and and all of these um you know
center surrounds like visual experiments
uh with no idea like how new they were
no idea like how um
new of an idea it was like the
processing through the visual cortex um
really like i didn't know how cutting
edge the work i was learning about was
so it's cool to kind of have that framed
for me
um and put in perspective and yeah all
the building upon that that's been done
it's nice
excellent
thank you very much blue and everybody
else who's participating and see you
next week
you